<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>ELIAS NEMA</title>
<link>https://www.eliasnema.com/data-feed.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://www.eliasnema.com/data-feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Making data work: analytics, personalisation, relevance and recommender systems - whatever is takes.</description>
<generator>quarto-1.7.32</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Sun, 19 Feb 2023 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Engineering Managers should Product et al.</title>
  <dc:creator>Elias Nema</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.eliasnema.com/state/product-engineering.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><strong>Summary: software engineers (especially leaders/managers up the tech hierarchy) should spend more time closer to the business, product, and marketing. They should treat it as part of their main responsibilities, not a nice-to-haves or if-have-times (which, of course, no one ever does).</strong></p>
<p>Some time ago, a tweet from Shreyas confirmed something I’ve also seen a lot – software engineering leadership focuses on technical problems, leaving business discussions to <em>“the business”,</em> or, more recently to <em>“the product”.</em> If not totally abandoning, then at least not thinking about this as a part of their main job – waiting for these magical stakeholders to have all the answers ready, while engineering will be focusing on tech things, prioritising tech debt, building internal tools, or what have you. I’m curious <strong>1/</strong> if that’s a software industry phenomenon, <strong>2/</strong> why is that happening, and <strong>3/</strong> what should engineers do, depending on the environment they are in.</p>
<center>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet blockquote">
<p lang="en" dir="ltr">
I am increasingly of the opinion that engineering leaders &amp; design leaders should be putting more pressure on their PM counterparts to <em>help devise</em> a sound product strategy. And this is absolutely vital if the business has been struggling. More process won’t solve this problem.
</p>
— Shreyas Doshi (<span class="citation" data-cites="shreyas">@shreyas</span>) <a href="https://twitter.com/shreyas/status/1616874874349445121?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 21, 2023</a>
</blockquote>
<script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
</center>
<section id="software" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="software">Software</h2>
<section id="stage-1-support-function" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="stage-1-support-function">Stage 1: Support Function</h3>
<p>In the early days of computers, IT was separate from business and played the role of a supporting function to automate some business processes and provide better business insights. Business innovations were happening outside the “computers”, and business is not growing by optimising and investing in software.</p>
<p>IT, as a support function, operates in a “ticketing machine” environment where things are regulated or already defined. An operational model of “just do what business tells” prevails and is also appropriate for such a setup.</p>
</section>
<section id="stage-2-transition-period-support-core" class="level3 page-columns page-full">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="stage-2-transition-period-support-core">Stage 2: Transition Period (Support → Core)</h3>
<p>Later on, software started percolating all the various areas of business and life and started to – famously – <strong>eat the world.</strong></p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Note
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>I don’t like this phrasing. It assumes that the endgame is only software, while I believe that the hardware will always be equally important, as proved recently by Apple and others – without the underlying layers, there will be nothing to build on top of.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><a href="going-soft.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="But regardless of the name, it’s still happening and going to continue in the foreseeable future."><img src="https://www.eliasnema.com/state/going-soft.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:35.0%" alt="But regardless of the name, it’s still happening and going to continue in the foreseeable future."></a></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">But regardless of the name, it’s still happening and going to continue in the <a href="https://www.economist.com/business/2022/06/12/how-supply-chain-turmoil-is-remaking-the-car-industry">foreseeable future.</a></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>This triggered a transition for software from a cost to a profit centre. It also exposed the ineffectiveness of the methods using rigid requirements and specifications, which, among other things, triggered the development of agile methodologies in software. These methods, however, attempted to fix the problem by establishing better interfaces between stakeholders. <strong>There was still a separation between the people who own the requirements, and the ones who implement them.</strong> However, this sets a trend of reducing dependencies and communication bottlenecks across different parts of building products.</p>
<p>But there is also an opposite force at work at the same time – software becomes more complex. This drives <strong>specialisation and more vertical knowledge.</strong> Technical experts need to go deeper and deeper to understand their topics at the same level. This, in turn, drives separation and creates a talent gap, where there are not enough people experienced in both technology and business. For example, Amazon was one of the first companies that separated the roles of product and engineering leadership, because it was hard to find people that were good at both.</p>
</section>
<section id="stage-3-software-is-product" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="stage-3-software-is-product">Stage 3: Software is Product</h3>
<p>This brings us to the period of more mature software products and development environments. It removes more interfaces and awards the role of the final judge to the <strong>customer.</strong> Software becomes a product in itself. There are even products <a href="https://blog.symops.com/2023/01/05/platform-engineering-as-a-startup/">within products.</a></p>
<p>Elimination of more silos is happening. DevOps, SREs, and continuous delivery movements, with cloud-enabling this transition on the underlying layer, removed final barriers between development, testing, and infrastructure. Engineering teams started working together to deliver a product and not a set of functional competencies.</p>
<p>We’ve learned to build software relatively fast and of good quality. However, we still do not always build what is needed for the user. The last gap standing is between engineering and business. This gap is responsible for creating engineering silos, <strong>software platforms that cannot support unit economics of business,</strong> and engineering for the sake of engineering, where you end up with systems inappropriately built for the size and scale of the business (no matter up or down), and cargo-culting with the best practices not adding value in a particular situation.</p>
<p>The reality is not evenly distributed, of course. Still, it’s happening way <a href="https://twitter.com/SergioRocks/status/1622959677431775235">too often</a> (so much that the opinion is still unpopular) in companies of all shapes and sizes. A lot of time business finds themselves <strong>hostage</strong> to tech decisions, not realising before that those decisions are actually business decisions now.</p>
<center>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet blockquote">
<p lang="en" dir="ltr">
to connect services to business through data.<br><br>"Business processes and domains were subordinate to applications."<br><br>This resonates, and I've multiple times seen the business end up hostage to the tech stack at some point in a company's evolution.
</p>
— Elias (<span class="citation" data-cites="eliasnema">@eliasnema</span>) <a href="https://twitter.com/eliasnema/status/1620543538772705280?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 31, 2023</a>
</blockquote>
<script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
</center>
</section>
</section>
<section id="other-industries" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="other-industries">Other industries</h2>
<p>At the beginning of my career, I worked in a couple of mechanical engineering companies, producing “real” objects. The environments I experienced there were a bit different from software, of course, but generally, engineers were <strong>not much closer</strong> to the product and business decisions. There were also no product managers to support them and close the gap.</p>
<p>This, however, still resulted in less over-engineered solutions or products that were completely off than I’ve seen working in software. But one explanation of this might be that when building physical products we have more constraints from the real world, while the <strong>possibility space is much wider</strong> with software. This increases variability in opinions and potential solution space, which makes communication through specifications even harder.</p>
<p>But going back in history, it turns out, that as with many problems, this one is also not new at all. Businesses started experiencing similar problems at least 70 years back when tech had yet nothing to do with software. Recently, I stumbled upon <a href="https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.1145/1434821.1434825">this paper from 1951</a> describing the changing role of management.</p>
<p>What’s fascinating is that already back then, the author notices that management nature changes, with factors such as human capital, research, and marketing starting to play as crucial of a role as science and engineering. <a href="../state/management-history.html">Here are more</a> quotes and thoughts from it.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><a href="mgmt-history.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Visual representation of 1951’s ‘New equations for management’"><img src="https://www.eliasnema.com/state/mgmt-history.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Visual representation of 1951’s ‘New equations for management’"></a></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Visual representation of 1951’s ‘New equations for management’</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Another example about is from Tony Fadell’s <a href="https://www.buildc.com/the-book">“Build”.</a> He writes how he learned the power of building relationships from his father becoming a top Levi’s salesman by playing long and establishing trust and relationships with his customers. And how successful companies are transitioning their sales setups from transaction-driven to relationship-driven cultures.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><a href="build-sales.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Tony Fadel on relationship-driven cultures"><img src="https://www.eliasnema.com/state/build-sales.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Tony Fadel on relationship-driven cultures"></a></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Tony Fadel on relationship-driven cultures</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>This quote is about sales organisations but goes the same way for the engineering-driven ones <em>(“we create a product, you just have to sell it”).</em></p>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>I don’t think that all companies will or should turn into software product companies. But you need to understand the environment you are in. And to converge sooner from Stage 2 to either 1 (cost) or 3 (profit).</p>
<p>The two competing factors in tech and management overall are not going away any time soon: tech still develops rapidly, complexity continues to grow, which drives <strong>specialisation.</strong> On the other hand, this leaves even less room for the defined requirements and specs, hence, creating a pull for <strong>cross-functional specialists.</strong></p>
<p>The main task of an engineering team is to deliver a product, of course. And your goal as a leader is <strong>to ensure this delivery.</strong> For this, you need to understand technology and engineering. But if the business you are working on has engineering at its core, your responsibilities stretch much further than just that:</p>
<ul>
<li>Understand <strong>people,</strong> and their motivations and build connections (this aspect is more universally accepted now).</li>
<li>Understand where your team’s value creation is happening in the <strong>business and marketing cycle.</strong></li>
<li>Tie the <strong>tech stack to the business decisions</strong> and make sure your team’s progress metrics are connected to the success of the overall company, not just the software development progress.</li>
<li><strong>Proactively build connections</strong> with product, marketing, legal, etc., or partially cover those roles yourself. Depending on the company you might have dedicated managers leading those directions, but that’s part of your role to proactively work with them on the engineering and business strategies.</li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>engineering</category>
  <category>leadership</category>
  <guid>https://www.eliasnema.com/state/product-engineering.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 19 Feb 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Paper: ‘New equations for management’, J. E. Hobson, 1951</title>
  <dc:creator>Elias Nema</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.eliasnema.com/state/management-history.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><em>My graphical representation of the <a href="https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.1145/1434821.1434825">paper</a>:</em></p>
<p><a href="mgmt-history.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1"><img src="https://www.eliasnema.com/state/mgmt-history.png" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p>Really interesting to see how research came into a “normal” state of business. I thought such things mich come naturally to the business as a market pull. However, you can see the role individual and government incentives have played to create the environment that would set up American companies for success for the next century.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<ul>
<li>Before most industrialists had given much thought to systematic efforts toward invention, Edison was keeping 75 men busy conducting experiments and designing and building new electrical apparatus so that he could make the use of electricity practical.</li>
<li>The rise of industrial research during the past thirty years as a factor in the management equation was brought about, or at least was accelerated, by a number of well planned actions outside of industry itself.
<ul>
<li>During the decade of the twenties, the National Research Council, through its Division of Engineering, conducted an organized promotional program designed to show industry why it should support applied research in its own interest.</li>
<li>Furthermore, the Department of Commerce, under Mr.&nbsp;Hoover’s Secretaryship, began a long-term effort to encourage American industry to engage in and support applied research.</li>
<li>One other major development should be mentioned. The first independent non-profit organization set up to provide research services to industry, the Mellon Research Foundation, came into being in 1915.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<p>Very interesting to see the logical sequence leading to the creation of “tech”: scarcity → abundance → need marketing to sell → more complex and fact-driven products → requires cross-functional collaboration → “techno-economics”.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<ul>
<li>The use of automatic machinery resulted in tremendous increases in productivity per man … [which gave birth to] the idea of mass production, lower unit profits, lower prices, mass consumption, higher wages, and generally speaking, higher net profits.</li>
<li>marketing had to be changed from one of “order taking” to one of aggressive selling to the mass market. Some of the great names in business over the last few decades are to</li>
<li>This marketing revolution brought with it a new need for an organized approach to fact-finding—economic and market research. The idea developed slowly—first in the eastern part of our country, then in the West. As industry has become more and more complex from a technological standpoint, the research functions in economics and in the physical sciences and engineering have inevitably been brought closer together. The resulting approach is now known in some quarters as “techno-economics.”</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<p>This also drives the change in the organisational structures, creating the demand for the development of the data industry:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<ul>
<li>As the size, complexity, and scope of industrial operations increased, there developed gradually a wholesale separation between management and ownership in much the same sense that labor and management divided at the beginning of the Industrial Revolution.</li>
<li>New types of instrumentation and devices of all sorts are being created to produce more complex products in greater quantities at lower cost.</li>
<li>The economist, the marketing research specialist, and the statistician are teamed with engineers, scientists, and mathematicians to refine the marketing factor in the management equation to a more exact point.</li>
<li>In human relations, management is seeking new ways to appreciate, understand, and evaluate motivations, reactions, group dynamics, and human engineering problems, whether they involve workers, executives, customers, or the general public.</li>
<li>effectiveness of communication, the quality of leadership, the temper of employee morale, the adjustment of men to machines and of machines to men, and the significance of the working environment can be analyzed, interpreted, and predicted.</li>
<li>This trend brings an ever-widening and more urgent demand on the part of management - for facts—economic facts about production costs and schedules, market potentials and requirements, inventories and prices; - technical facts about new products and processes; - and social science facts about people and their patterns of behavior.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<p>Considering recent tech layoffs and general rethinking of the effectiveness of latge orgs, this quote is quite timely:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>In attempting to achieve a more efficient operation to go along with the increasing complexity of industrial affairs, management has also given serious thought during recent years to the size and location of its organizational units. We hear more about the problem of size versus morale and efficiency. Some companies have taken the position that definite limits should be placed upon the size of a single operating group. Others are striving to place parts of their organization in suburban settings.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Administrative revolution …</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>it is conceivable that future business historians will know this period as the beginning of the “administrative revolution.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Here is also a thread with a few more excerpts:</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet blockquote">
<p lang="en" dir="ltr">
With seemingly lots of mismanagement happening recently, I got curious about the history of management, and found the industry view from 1951 - a paper called "New equations for management".<br>Here is a visual summary I made, and a few excerpts from the paper I found interesting / <a href="https://t.co/kMYTWI4PSl">pic.twitter.com/kMYTWI4PSl</a>
</p>
— Elias Nema (<span class="citation" data-cites="eliasnema">@eliasnema</span>) <a href="https://twitter.com/eliasnema/status/1621149904424013824?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">February 2, 2023</a>
</blockquote>
<script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>



 ]]></description>
  <category>engineering</category>
  <category>leadership</category>
  <guid>https://www.eliasnema.com/state/management-history.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>State of Recommendations</title>
  <dc:creator>Elias Nema</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.eliasnema.com/state/state-of-reco.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="overview" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="overview">Overview</h2>
<p>This is a lengthy piece covering 6 articles, 4 papers and demonstrating trends happening in the field of <strong>applied recommender systems</strong>. Cases below will be structured as follows:</p>
<div class="cell" data-layout-align="default">
<div class="cell-output-display">
<div>
<p></p><figure class="figure"><p></p>
<div>
<pre class="mermaid mermaid-js">flowchart LR
  A(Overview) --&gt; B(Data)
  B --&gt; C(Model)
  C --&gt; D(Validation)
  D --&gt; E(Production)
</pre>
</div>
<p></p></figure><p></p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>I prefer not to focus on the reported results because they are usually relative to the previous baselines and easily interpreted outside the context.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.eliasnema.com/state/reco.png" class="figure-img" alt="Fig 1. Summary of Trends" width="500"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Fig 1. Summary of Trends</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<ul>
<li>Starting back in the days with a timeless classic of recsys — matrix factorization, it’s now hard to find a system without some kind of <strong>neural nets, embedding spaces or sequential models.</strong></li>
<li>Serving has also moved to more <strong>real-time</strong> architectures and dynamic <strong>re-rankers.</strong> Not to mention that generally, the focus now is <strong>much more on the system as a whole</strong>, rather than just a modeling part.</li>
<li>Moving from relying mostly on explicit ratings to incorporating different <strong>implicit</strong> signals and giving them weights. Hence, also the <strong>regression→classification</strong> shift.</li>
<li>On the <strong>item side</strong> pretty much every one converged to building embeddings to optimize for the product similarity.</li>
<li>On the <strong>user side,</strong> however, representations vary depending on the use case and business model.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<p>But the truth is in details, so let’s dive in.</p>
</section>
<section id="linkedin" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="linkedin"><img src="https://www.eliasnema.com/state/linkedin.png" width="35"> LinkedIn</h2>
<section id="linkedin-learning" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="linkedin-learning">LinkedIn Learning</h3>
<p>We start with the LinkedIn Learning use case and their two-part article (<a href="https://engineering.linkedin.com/blog/2020/course-recommendations-ai-part-one">one</a>, <a href="https://engineering.linkedin.com/blog/2020/course-recommendations-ai-part-two">two</a>). The main goal for them is to <em>“surface the most relevant and personalized course recommendations”</em>.</p>
<p>At LinkedIn, two main models are powering the offline (precalculated for each user daily) recommendations — <strong>neural collaborative filtering</strong> and <strong>“response prediction” model.</strong></p>
<section id="linkedin-learning-collaborative-filtering-neural" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="linkedin-learning-collaborative-filtering-neural">LinkedIn Learning: Collaborative Filtering (Neural)</h4>
<p>Pros/cons of CF are well-known and LinkedIn didn’t escape them. Here is their recap:</p>
<ul>
<li>works better for core learners (members who are already active on the LinkedIn Learning platform)</li>
<li>focuses on recent interactions <em>(not a very common one, probably a property of their implementation)</em></li>
<li>diversified recommendations, no domain knowledge needed, however, cold start problems</li>
</ul>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>I think recency and diversity are the most interesting points here.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Recency:</strong> generally, CF doesn’t give preference for the recent items unless implemented with some kind of time decay or position-aware component in the model.</li>
<li><strong>Diversity:</strong> in e-commerce, CF often <strong>reduces</strong> diversity because of the rich-get-richer effect. And here, probably, due to the fact that the course catalog is not that big and that every person can take any course, it actually increases it.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<p><strong>🛢Data:</strong> course watch history data with a watch-time threshold (if a learner only watches the first three seconds of a course, it’s not included).</p>
<p><strong>🚗Model:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Computing learner and course embeddings in parallel. This is also known as a <em>two-tower architecture.</em></li>
<li>Log loss is used as an optimization function.</li>
<li>The modeling objective is to predict course watches using the past watches.</li>
<li>4 negative samples are taken for each positive one.</li>
<li>Holding the last interaction for each user for a test set — a <strong>leave-one-out</strong> approach.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Two-tower architecture consists of two networks with fully connected layers in each becoming narrower with each consecutive layer.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><strong>🔁Validation:</strong> A random sample of 100 items that user didn’t interact with is taken and the one hidden item (user’s last action) is ranked against these 100. Performance is judged by <strong>hit ratio and NDCG</strong> at 10.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Interesting that input to the learner part is <strong>user/course co-occurrence matrix</strong>, while input to the course part is <strong>course/course similarity</strong> matrix.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><strong>🎬Production:</strong> Generating top K courses for each user based on the similarity between embeddings. Calculating offline and storing in a key-value storage.</p>
</section>
<section id="linkedin-learning-response-prediction-model" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="linkedin-learning-response-prediction-model">LinkedIn Learning: Response Prediction Model</h4>
<p>Another offline model to compliment CF is so-called “Response Prediction”. It takes into account user and course metadata as well as user’s actions.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>This algorithm typically performs better than CF for members with no/little previous engagement on LinkedIn Learning, as well as for new courses with few prior interactions.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><strong>🛢Data</strong>:</p>
<ul>
<li>User profile features (skills, industry, etc.)</li>
<li>Course metadata (difficulty, category, skills)</li>
<li>Historical explicit engagement (clicks, bookmarks, etc.) with the course watch time as an importance weight given to each click instance.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>As a result, this importance weight helps to promote courses with higher watch times and creates a model that can optimize for course watches, not just clicks.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><strong>🚗Model</strong>: a fancy named “Generalized Linear Mixture Model (GLMix)” is used here. In reality, it’s quite a simple (though hard computationally, <a href="https://www.kdd.org/kdd2016/papers/files/adf0562-zhangA.pdf">check the paper</a>) approach to express user’s probability to click via a sum of the three components: a global model, per-learner model, and per-course model.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>We are currently working on a model ensemble that can perform personalized blending of Response Prediction and Neural CF models to improve the overall performance on the final recommendation task. Secondly, we also plan to adopt Attention Models into our Neural CF framework for learner profiling, i.e., assigning attention weights to a learner’s course watch history to capture long term and short term interests in a more effective manner.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><strong>🔁Validation:</strong> AUC for offline validation as well as click/apply rates for the online experiments.</p>
<p><strong>🎬Production:</strong> offline two-stage ranking strategy.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>storing courses and their features in Lucene, after, using features of users to generate 1000 candidates for each</li>
<li>ranking candidates using full GLMix model</li>
</ol>
</section>
</section>
<section id="linkedin-jobs" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="linkedin-jobs">LinkedIn Jobs</h3>
<p>In their <a href="https://engineering.linkedin.com/blog/2020/quality-matches-via-personalized-ai">next article,</a> LinkedIn shared some insights on their jobs recommendations <strong>(which can potentially be useful for any job-seeker).</strong> For example:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Our analysis demonstrated that the majority of job applicants <strong>apply to at least 5 jobs</strong>, while the majority of <strong>job postings receive at least 10 applicants</strong>. This proves to result in enough data to train the personalization models.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><strong>Goal</strong>: to predict the probability of a positive recruiter action, conditional on a given member applying to a given job.</p>
<p><strong>🛢Data</strong>: how to identify if a signal is negative (have someone not replied because of lack of interest or because he is processing other candidates)? &gt; We make the negatives conclusive if no engagement is seen after 14 days. However, if a recruiter responds to other applications submitted later, we may infer the negative label earlier.</p>
<p>Now you know when to stop waiting for the recruiter’s response ⏳.</p>
<p><strong>🚗Model</strong>: here, the same model from the above (GLMix).</p>
<div class="line-block">logit(P(positive response | member, job)) =<br>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<code>F_global(X_member, X_job) + F_member(X_job) + F_job(X_member)</code></div>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>We used linear models for fm and fj, but one <strong>can use any model in the above formulation as long as the produced scores are calibrated to output log-odds</strong> (for example, a neural net). Usually, linear models are sufficient as per-member and per-job components, as individual members and individual jobs <strong>do not have enough interactions</strong> to train more complex non-linear models.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><strong>🔁Validation</strong>: AUC and NDCG are used.</p>
<p><strong>🎬Production</strong>:</p>
<ul>
<li>user/job models are retrained daily, with automated quality checks in place</li>
<li>global model his updated once every few weeks</li>
<li>initializing weights with existing values to reduce the training time</li>
</ul>
<p>You can see that features of your profile play a very important role when you are searching for a job, so if you are looking for something specific, <strong>make sure to include the relevant signals into your profile at least a couple of days before.</strong></p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="avito" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="avito"><img src="https://www.eliasnema.com/state/avito.png" width="35"> Avito</h2>
<p>A very <a href="https://habr.com/ru/company/avito/blog/491942/">important and thoughtful article</a> (in Russian) from our friends at Avito. And their approach takes a bit different direction. What if instead of learning personalized recommendations we’d try to optimize for the <strong>item similarity</strong>?</p>
<p><strong>🛢Data:</strong> pairs of “similar” items.</p>
<p>How to define similars? Items that were “contacted” (the best proxy for the transaction in classifieds) by a user with a time threshold between actions (8h for Avito). This gives 1s as a label. How to get 0s? Negative sampling from the items that were active at the platform during the time of contact but were not selected by the user.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Random sampling with a probability of an item being selected equals to a <strong>square root of a number of contacts that this item got</strong> (how popular the item was).</p>
</blockquote>
<p><strong>🚗Model:</strong> item features are fed into the embedding layers with a dropout and 2 linear layers on top. <strong>Item IDs are not included</strong> into item features to allow for model generalization.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>The last layer is tanh to transform the output into the [-1, 1] range and <strong>multiply by 128</strong> later to fit into the INT8 to save memory in serving.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Calculating scores for the positive sample and 4000 (the more — the better, constraint of the GPU memory) negative samples for each pair. Taking highest scores from the negatives (top 100 wrongly predicted items) and computing the log-loss.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Learning only from the top 100 wrong predictions allows to <strong>save on training time without loosing the accuracy</strong>.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><strong>🔁Validation:</strong> precision at 8 is calculated on a test set. Time-based split, with <strong>omitting 6 months</strong> of data between training and validation. This is done to see how model will behave after 6 months of not training.</p>
<p><strong>🎬Production:</strong> The model is re-trained once per 6 months. This works fine because item IDs are not included into training so new items can be embedded into the space just by their features. So new items get’s represented in a space as soon as they are posted. Embeddings are stored in Sphinx search engine, which allows quite a fast vector search (p99 is under 200ms with 200k rpm, sharded by category).</p>
<p>Recommendations are used on both the item page (item-to-item) and the homefeed (user-to-item), with user-to-item generated from the similar items to the ones that user has seen recently.</p>
</section>
<section id="pinterest" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pinterest"><img src="https://www.eliasnema.com/state/pinterest.png" width="35"> Pinterest</h2>
<p>And now — Pinterest. Another very thoughtful and pragmatic <a href="https://medium.com/pinterest-engineering/pinnersage-multi-modal-user-embedding-framework-for-recommendations-at-pinterest-bfd116b49475">piece from them</a>.</p>
<p>Here as well, the general idea is to embed users/items into some space. However, having a single vector for user works bad — no matter how good the network is it won’t be able to represent all the clusters of user’s interests. Another approach (the same as Avito takes above) is to represent <strong>a user via embeddings of items</strong> that he is interested in. But averaging of embeddings works bad for the longer-term user interests (e.g.&nbsp;<a href="https://miro.medium.com/max/1400/0*KB50oLyVlnzoGuen">paintings and shoes average to a salad</a>). The solution?</p>
<p>Run <strong>clustering</strong> on the user’s actions and take <strong>medoids</strong> (like centroids, but should be an existing item) from the most important clusters. Find similar items to those medoids.</p>
<p><strong>🛢Data:</strong> users’ action pins from the last 90 days.</p>
<p><strong>🚗Model:</strong> the main model is quite a simple <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ward%27s_method">Ward clustering</a> with the goal to produce different amount of clusters depending on a variety of items in the user’s history. A time decay average is used to assign importance to clusters.</p>
<p><strong>🔁Validation:</strong> a very thorough approach to the evaluation process, highly recommend to check out more in the <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2007.03634.pdf">paper</a>.</p>
<ul>
<li>Cluster user’s actions and rank clusters by importance.</li>
<li>Get 400 closest items to the medoids of the most important clusters.</li>
<li>Calculate <strong>relevance:</strong> the proportion of observed action pins that have high cosine similarity (≥0.8) with any recommended pin.</li>
<li>And <strong>recall:</strong> the proportion of action pins that are found in the recommendation set.</li>
<li>Test batches are calculated in the chronological order, day by day, simulating the production setup.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>🎬Production</strong>:</p>
<ul>
<li>Using HNSW for the approximate nearest neighbor search</li>
<li>Filtering out near-duplicates and lower quality pins</li>
<li>Using medoids allows saving on caching (no need to compute aNN all the time)</li>
</ul>
<p>Served using a classical <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lambda_architecture">lambda architecture</a>:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<ol type="1">
<li>Daily Batch Inference: PinnerSage is run daily over the <strong>last 90 day actions</strong> of a user on a MapReduce cluster. The output of the daily inference job (list of medoids and their importance) are served online in key-value store.</li>
<li>Lightweight Online Inference: We collect the <strong>most recent 20 actions</strong> of each user on the latest day (after the last update to the entry in the key-value store) for online inference. PinnerSage uses a real-time event-based streaming service to consume action events and update the clusters initiated from the key-value store.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>In practice, the system optimization plays a critical role in enabling the productionization of PinnerSage.</strong></p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="coveo-coveo" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="coveo-coveo"><img src="https://www.eliasnema.com/state/coveo.png" width="35" alt="coveo"> Coveo</h2>
<p>Ok, item embeddings are great. But how about transfer learning for them? Wait, what? The thing is that many companies are actually multi-brand groups having more than one website.</p>
<p>Training embeddings for similar products in different shops will produce spaces which are not comparable. Is there a way to mitigate this? You bet there is.</p>
<p><strong>🛢Data:</strong> the best part is that you don’t need tons of data. All you need is data on how users interacted with products within sessions to build product spaces. After that, product features will come handy (text attributes, prices, images, etc.) to align spaces. Having <strong>cross-shop data</strong> is valuable later but not strictly necessary.</p>
<p><strong>🚗Model:</strong> product embeddings are trained using CBOW with negative sampling, by swapping the concept of words in a sentence with products in a browsing session. This is not the fanciest architecture for item embeddings — check the Avito implementation above for a more sophisticated approach.</p>
<p>More interestingly though is a task to <strong>align product spaces</strong>. It’s different from aligning spaces for languages, mainly, because languanes are guaranteed to have similiar concepts, while for some products it’s not necesseraly true. Coveo has tried different models, but the general approach is:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Start with some unsupervised approach, such as pairing by item features, images, etc. This helps finding the initial mapping function.</li>
<li>Later, adjust the space alignment by learning from user interactions with the items in different spaces.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>🔁Validation:</strong> for the product embeddings model evaluation is done using the leave-one-out approach and by predicting the Nth interactions from the 0..N-1 items: embeddings are averaged for 0..N-1 items and the nearest neighbor search is done to predict the Nth item. NDCG@10 is used on the search result.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Worth noting that this approach works for the short-lived sessions or specialized shops, while for sessions with multiple intents averaging might produce really weird results (see the Pinterest case above).</p>
</blockquote>
<p><strong>🎬Production</strong>: they run 2 experiments. In both, the idea was to use an intent from one shop and aligned embeddings to</p>
<ul>
<li>predict the user’s next action</li>
<li>predict the best query in the search autocomplete</li>
</ul>
<p>Both experiments have proven the potential behind the approach and I’ll be paying a close attention to the area of transfer learning for product spaces in the future.</p>
<hr>
<p><br> References:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><a href="https://engineering.linkedin.com/blog/2020/course-recommendations-ai-part-one">LinkedIn’s Learning Recommendations Part 1</a></li>
<li><a href="https://engineering.linkedin.com/blog/2020/course-recommendations-ai-part-two">LinkedIn’s Learning Recommendations Part 2</a></li>
<li><a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1708.05031.pdf">LinkedIn’s Neural Collaborative Filtering</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.kdd.org/kdd2016/papers/files/adf0562-zhangA.pdf">LinkedIn’s Generalized Linear Mixed Models</a></li>
<li><a href="https://engineering.linkedin.com/blog/2020/quality-matches-via-personalized-ai">LinkedIn Jobs’ article</a></li>
<li>Avito’s <a href="https://habr.com/ru/company/avito/blog/491942/">article</a></li>
<li>Pinterest’s <a href="https://medium.com/pinterest-engineering/pinnersage-multi-modal-user-embedding-framework-for-recommendations-at-pinterest-bfd116b49475">article</a></li>
<li>Pinterest’s <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2007.03634.pdf">paper</a></li>
<li>Coveo’s blog posts: <a href="https://blog.coveo.com/multi-brand-personalization-in-ecommerce/">one</a>, <a href="https://blog.coveo.com/clothes-in-space-real-time-personalization-in-less-than-100-lines-of-code/">two</a></li>
<li>Coveo’s <a href="https://blog.coveo.com/multi-brand-personalization-in-ecommerce/">paper</a></li>
<li><a href="https://developers.google.com/machine-learning/recommendation/dnn/softmax#can-you-use-item-features">Intro to recommendations</a> by Google</li>
</ol>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>recommendations</category>
  <guid>https://www.eliasnema.com/state/state-of-reco.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 04 Sep 2020 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
